Okay we're continuing here on ל"ב עמוד א' Lamed Bet Amud Aleph
about 10 lines from the bottom. Okay, so we have the משנה
Mishna that says that you cannot be פוחת הנר, pochet haneir, which
רש"י, Rashi, which תוספות Tosfos says means you cannot remove the stuffing
after the first firing of this
lamp, it hasn't finished hardening because that would be like making it
a vessel. And we want to see, who is the תנא Tanna
that says that removing something before it's sort of finished being hardened
is still considered a vessel? So first we compared it to a
general statement about pottery or vessels, which תוספות Tosfos understood again was
talking exactly about this, that once the stuffing is removed before the
second firing. And now we are talking about these frying pans, where
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says that even while they have the
cover on they're still a vessel, so they're a vessel at an
earlier stage even with the cover on and we'll see why, how
can you use a frying pan when it still has the cover
is sealed on and not removed? But רבי אליעזר ברבי צדוק Rebbi
Eliezer berabbi Tzadok says no, he says לפי שלא נגמר מלאכתן, lefi
shelo nigmar melachtan,
their work isn't done, which again is understood to mean the top
hasn't been removed. But once the top is removed, presumably again even
if you have not yet finished hardening it and firing it, it
would be a vessel. So for רבי אליעזר ברבי צדוק Rebbi Eliezer
berabbi Tzadok the removing of this obstruction makes it a vessel even
after even before presumably the firing and the hardening process has completed.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, same question. אמר ליה אביי
Amar lei Abaye so אביי Abaye said back דילמא dilma maybe not
true. דילמא עד כאן לא קאמר רבי אליעזר ברבי צדוק התם, dilma
ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Eliezer berabbi Tzadok hatam, maybe רבי אליעזר
ברבי צדוק Rebbi Eliezer berabbi Tzadok only said it there אלא דחזי
לקיבולי ביה מידי ela dechazi lekippulei bei midi
because once you've removed the cover of a frying pan even if
it hasn't finished hardening you can still use it for storing things
and for putting things in it. אבל הכא aval hacha here this
tiny little
lamp למאי חזי lemai chazi what good is it going to do,
it has no purpose. It says yes לקיבולי ביה פשיטי lekippulei bei
peshiti you can put little objects into it and therefore you can
use it. So the גמרא Gemara again is saying that our משנה
Mishna is saying you cannot remove the stuffing or this obstruction that's
part of the process of making a vessel, and the act of
removing it even before it's hardened is like making it into a
vessel. And the גמרא Gemara compared it to two different תנאים Tannaim
in different debates by טומאה
וטהרה, Tumah ve'Taharah, by when is a vessel susceptible to, is this
a vessel at the stage where this is removed before it has
finished being hardened? Okay, let's run one minute, let's just finish up
this issue about these Bilgi's frying pans. So the גמרא Gemara says
תנו רבנן אין
פוחתין את הנר ואין עושין אילפס אילפסין חרניות ביום טוב. Tanu Rabbanan
ein pochtin et haneir ve'ein osin ilpas ilpasin charaniot beYom Tov. So
here interestingly we have a ברייתא Baraisa that combines this, you know,
this second discussion of טומאה וטהרה Tumah ve'Taharah in our יום טוב
Yom Tov discussion. So the same way you cannot remove the filling
from the lamp before it's finished even before it's finished hardening, you
cannot also make these frying pans, these village frying pans, which again
presumably would mean that you can't, you know, like remove the cover
the way תוספות Tosfos has understood it. Okay so the גמרא Gemara
says רבן שמעון בן גמליאל מתיר באילפין חרניות Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
matir be'ilfin charaniot and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
allows it. So again maybe exactly this same type of a question
of whether they are considered at what stage are they considered to
be finished or a vessel or not. So the גמרא Gemara says
מאי חרניות mai charaniot and what does this mean? We've been talking
about these חרניות charaniot vessels, what does that mean? So the גמרא
Gemara says אמר רב יהודה אירניות, Amar Rav Yehuda iraniot, village, village
frying pans. מאי אירניות mai iraniot what does that mean? So אמר
אביי צחי חקלאיתא Amar Abaye tzachei chaklaita okay they means basically plates
that are used out in the field because basically what do you
do with a frying pan that still has the cover on it?
Well what you do with a frying pan that still has the
cover on it is that you could still use it as a
platter until you've got the cover removed. So therefore that's why these
are called these village frying pans. It's true they still have the
cover sealed on and haven't been removed, but they might want but,
you know, out in the villages where they're not so fancy they
might be prepared to use them at that stage so they could
use them as a type of a platter. Yes you had a
question?
Would you say is it actually in your opinion to say that
the מחלוקת machlokes here is whether the definition is functional or formalistic,
right?
Whether you
can use to receive things or not it's useful enough. So it's
about whether the, I don't care whether it's useful or not, it's
not done, the cover is still on.
Yeah in some
ways there's two different modes of thought going on behind the, right,
the intertwined.
You mean one is just saying, right, even though it has a
function it is in an objective sense it has not really finished
being processed.
Right.
Response formalism? Yeah that's true, that's true, yes.
Okay one minute.
Fine. So now let's go on so the גמרא Gemara says like
this, okay we just did that. Okay so we're now done with
the issue about making a vessel so again. Obviously you can't, like
תוספות Tosfos says פשיטא, p'shita, nobody would think you could start molding
clay, but the question is at a certain middle stage and removing
something and how much have you really made it a vessel, how
much have you finished it, how much was it not a vessel
beforehand, that's sort of what's being debated here. And again the interesting
point is that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is part of this discussion
in the משנה Mishna even though he says you could do מכשירי
אוכל נפש machshirei ochel nefesh which is again a demonstration that רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda could agree that if it's an issue of actually
making a vessel that makes it in a different category. Okay now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: ואין עושין פחמין, ve'ein osin pechamin,
you cannot make charcoal. פשיטא, p'shita, obvious. למאי חזי, lemai chazi, what
are you going to use it for? Now that's a funny question.
What do you mean למאי חזי? lemai chazi? Who cares what you're
going to use it for? You can't make it because, you know,
what does not being able to be used for something make it
obvious why you can't do it? So it's going to seem from
the גמרא's Gemara's answer that the point is like this. Look, you
can make a fire on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So and again
not a new fire. So maybe if you were using this charcoal
for cooking, maybe you would be able to, maybe you could. What
would be so bad? Right? It's like making a fire. But the
גמרא's Gemara's saying, yeah, but you don't use charcoal for cooking. So
you don't use charcoal for cooking, what do you use it for?
So I mean I guess they didn't have like we have like
these grills where the whole point is to keep it at a
charcoal level and so on. So basically you would use it primarily
for רש''י Rashi says for like smelting metal and in metal work.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara says, so of course you can't
make. There's no אוכל נפש ochel nefesh value here. What would be
the הוה אמינא? hava amina? So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara's
answer is.
So the גמרא Gemara says, תני רבי חייא, tani Rabbi Chiyya, לא
נצרכה אלא למסרן לאוליירין, lo nitzrecha ela lemosran le'ulyarin, בו ביום. bo
bayom. No,
maybe you wanted to use it for something you thought was a
legitimate use. You were going to give it over to the to
the bathhouse workers and the people that heat up the water in
the bathhouse. Okay, and therefore you might think, okay, well you're allowed
to have hot water, you're allowed to heat up water for bathing
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, right? So that is אוכל נפש. ochel
nefesh. So that should be allowed.
So יום טוב Yom Tov also שמחה, simcha, no?
Yeah, but besides שמחה simcha you're not allowed סתם שמחה stam simcha
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, it has to be in the אוכל
נפש ochel nefesh category. Okay, so you're allowed to heat up water
for bathing, that's considered something on the body and it's צורך כל
גופו, tzorech kol gufo, etc. So therefore maybe you know you should
also be able to make the charcoal that's used in these bathhouses.
So the גמרא Gemara says בו ביום נשתרו? bo bayom nishtero? One
minute, says the גמרא, Gemara, since when can you use, you know,
go into a heated water bathhouse even on יום טוב? Yom Tov?
Because why not? Because there actually is a הלכה halacha and this
is, you know, important even nowadays, which is that חז''ל Chazal did
not let people go into a bathhouse on שבת Shabbos even if
the water was heated before שבת. Shabbos. Why not? Because once you
start letting people use the bathhouses with preheated water, they're going to
come to use the bathhouses with water that's heated on שבת. Shabbos.
פשיטא. p'shita. That makes sense on שבת. Shabbos. But how about יום
טוב? Yom Tov? On יום טוב Yom Tov if you would heat
the water on יום טוב Yom Tov it wouldn't be a big
deal. Now maybe it would, we've discussed before that maybe at least
in the time of the גמרא Gemara that heating water for your
face and legs or whatever, that would be a normal type of
a use, but water for your whole body maybe wouldn't be considered
as universal a use. But anyway, however you understand it, you know,
the גמרא Gemara makes it clear that this גזירת מרחצאות gzeirat merchataot
applied not only on שבת Shabbos but even on יום טוב, Yom
Tov, even though on יום טוב Yom Tov it might if it
might even be permissible to heat the water under certain circumstances. But
nevertheless the bathhouses were totally off-limits even on יום טוב. Yom Tov.
So if that's true, now that's I'll tell you why that's relevant
in a minute. But if that's true says the גמרא, Gemara, what
do you mean? Well, I could have used the charcoal for bathhouses.
Bathhouses are off-limits on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Right? Even if the
heating water is צורך כל גוף, tzorech kol guf, the bathhouse use
is off-limits. So how, so what would you have used it for?
So the גמרא Gemara says, no, כי הא דאמר רבא, ki ha
de'amar Rava, להזיע, lehazia, to sweat. Which is even when they forbade
initially the bathhouses, they did not forbid initially the sauna part of
the bathhouses. So to use steam, again it's funny because you would
think if anything you're more likely to do a מלאכה melacha on
the day itself, it would be the creating of the steam, not
the heating up and the retaining of the water. But they also
had ways to keep the steam like in a room below and
plugged up and then you would release it. Anyway, we'll see about
that more later, but basically the point
initially the point was was that they did not forbid you to
use the steam house. So here at that stage when the steam
was not yet forbidden, you want to heat up charcoal and use
it to for your sauna on יום טוב. Yom Tov. It's צורך
כל גוף tzorech kol guf and it's not forbidden רבנן, rabanan, and
that's what you want to do. And the משנה Mishna says even
if that's a legitimate use you cannot go be making charcoal on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. So the גמרא Gemara says וקודם גזירה, vekodem
gzeira, before they forbade the steam, before the גזירה gzeira about using
the sauna. So התם נמי, hasam nami, so he says that in
a different context. So here also להזיע וקודם גזירה, lehazia vekodem gzeira,
where he'd be talking about that context that you wanted to use
it for a sauna before the גזירה, gzeira, so it was a
legitimate use and nevertheless you can't do it. Now again this is
important because this... underscores,
I don't know if that's the word, underscores again the point that
that that even if it's צורך כל הגוף, tzorech kol haguf, even
if it's a type of an אוכל נפש ochel nefesh which like
hot water and so on for the body is generally concerned, considered,
you cannot make a vessel for that purpose. And even ר' יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda who allows מכשירי אוכל נפש, machshirei ochel nefesh, because ר'
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda is in the משנה, Mishnah, seems to not debate
this point, that he will not let you make charcoal even if
it is for the purpose of something that is a צורך, tzorech,
you know, that is a, that is a צורך אוכל נפש. tzorech
ochel nefesh. So again, for us I think it's a little funny
to think of charcoal as a כלי, kli, but you know, why
not? It's like something you took a piece of wood, you fashioned
it in a certain way, you used fire to fashion it in
a certain way, and now it's usable to do something with.
Right, but it's כיבוי kibuy is not necessarily...
well right, we don't always use the, what do you call it,
the טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah criteria. So you can make a fire,
but if you're actually making the כלי kli for the fire, right,
like according to ר' יהודה Rebbi Yehuda who allows מכשירי אוכל נפש,
machshirei ochel nefesh, would he let me dig out a fireplace, you
know, would he let me like make a grill on יום טוב?
Yom Tov? So, so this is the issue. So here too you
can't make the charcoal, okay? And therefore that is consider- even if
מכשירי אוכל נפש machshirei ochel nefesh allowed, making a something that's like
a כלי kli and has this greater sense of long term and
permanence and so on, that is going to be a problem even
according to ר' יהודה Rebbi Yehuda and that's the problem here even
if you found a legitimate use like to use it for steam
or to use it on your grill. Now the other thing I
want to say, and again we'll see this when we also get
to the גזירת מרחצאות, gezeiras merchatzahos, actually we might have done that
already in שבת, Shabbos, we might not be seeing it again anyway,
but this is very relevant for the issue of taking a hot
shower on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Because according to גמרא, Gemara, בית
הלל ובית שמאי, Beis Hillel v'Beis Shammai, you might remember that בית
הלל Beis Hillel lets you heat up hot water for using for
פניו ידיו ורגליו, panav yadav v'raglav, but not for כל גופו, kol
gufo, right? Now, why not? So תוספות Tosafot says, well you know,
hot water for your whole body, that's not a universal need. Face
and hands and arms, yes, but you know, not everybody really needs
this, so מפונק mefunak fancy that they need to bathe their whole
body in hot water. So according to that, many, you know, פוסקים
poskim say that nowadays where obviously it is a very universal need
and on a, you know, for many people on a daily basis,
I think sometimes there's differences in certain like countries whether, you know,
how much they see daily bathing, but nevertheless, you know, that it
would totally be a צורך כל הגוף tzorech kol haguf and that
you could take a hot shower on יום טוב. Yom Tov. And
there's no problem even if normally, you know, whatever, assuming you normally,
you know, assuming one won't get into that whole discussion about if
you live in an apartment building and can you use the hot
water whatever, assuming we generally assume you can't use the hot water
whether for whatever the reason is, you know, let's say it's the
case of a house, so the use of the hot water will
almost always lead to other water being... okay, I'm going on a
digression. Anyway, assuming that you're not generally using hot water on שבת,
Shabbos, on שבת Shabbos you can- on יום טוב Yom Tov you
can take a hot water- you can take a shower on יום
טוב Yom Tov because that's a צורך כל הגוף. tzorech kol haguf.
Now not everybody agrees, but many many פוסקים poskim do say that.
However, even though you can take a hot shower on יום טוב
Yom Tov because it's again, you know, cooking or fire related but
it's all about something that's a universal bodily need, so it's like
אוכל נפש, ochel nefesh, you can't take a hot bath. Because a
hot bath remains in the גזירת מרחצאות. gezeiras merchatzahos. So that remains
rabbinically forbidden based on this whole issue of the bathhouses, even if
you're still allowed to take a hot shower. Yes, Charlie?
But people are immersing in מקווה mikvah on even on שבת? Shabbos?
Yes, okay, so there's a lot of פוסקים poskim that try to
figure out why, and but we'll bracket that for now.
This is the same issue as in במה מדליקין Bameh Madlikin with
the פתילות pesilos whether it turns into a כלי kli or not.
Yeah, that's related. There, right, there it's more about הבערה, havarah, about
כיבוי kibuy being a, being like a constructive type of an act,
a מלאכה שצריכה לגופה, melachah she'tzrichah l'gufah, but it's related to the
idea certainly that charcoal or whatever is considered to be something that's
being made. Okay, so now the, yes?
When's the issue of steam used by somebody that wants to take
a bath?
Yeah, so that's a good question and I think even beyond that
there's like, as I said, although not necessarily, you see a lot
of people that go and they just want to sit in the
sauna and they're not interested in the bath. But I think the
bigger question is like, isn't steam even a bigger concern that you'll
come to violate שבת Shabbos or יום טוב Yom Tov in the
making of the steam? But for now we're just going to bracket
that. It's a good question. Yes?
But what is it a כלי, kli, then? I assume it's a
vessel. כלי kli it is.
But that's what I'm saying. So how do you define what a
vessel is? Meaning why isn't something that's used in that I, you
know, why is charcoal not a vessel? I think the only reason
we think that it's not a vessel is because we think of
a vessel as something that having, that endures. No, not that holds,
I think we think I think the reason if you ask me
is charcoal a vessel, no it's not a vessel, you use it
up, right? But you know, so it gets destroyed in the process.
But like would I consider to be, I don't know, a wrapping
paper or some type of like, you know, disposable thing a vessel?
But I think I would say yes. But a Ziploc bag gets
reused. But let's say it's something... that's completely one-time disposable use, you
know, right, you know, do I consider it a vessel? I don't
know, I think I do. And I think I do somehow more
than I do a charcoal, maybe because charcoal the way you use
it is by destroying it. So there is, but you know, it's
an interesting question, you're right, that some intuitive sense, we don't, I
don't think we think of charcoal as a vessel and the גמרא
Gemara and the גמרא Gemara is. I actually heard an interesting thing
the other day, which is about how do we think about categories,
you know, that's goes back to the whole idea of like this
Platonic idea that like they've done studies and if like you ask
people like is this thing a fruit? Most people won't think like
of abstract criteria of what makes a fruit, they'll think about their
paradigm fruit, for most people it's an apple, and they'll ask themselves
is this like an apple enough or not? You know, so that's
how like we sort of think about does it fit into a
category, we think about the thing for us that represents the category,
say, oh, is this close enough to that? So anyway. All right,
some reason for us charcoal doesn't fit into the כלי kli category.
I agree with you. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. ואין
חותכין את הפתילה לשנים. Ve'ein chotzin et haptilah lishnayim.
So you cannot cut a wick into two, that's also like making
it a vessel. By the way, that's interesting also because you know
you could say well I didn't add functionality, right? Before it was
usable, now it's usable, it's just now it's a better size to
use and it's not as wasteful or whatever. You know now I
don't know again maybe you do add functionality, maybe if you have
too long of a wick in a lamp maybe the oil is
drawn at a different rate or something like that. But you know
this gets to the question of like cutting toilet paper and cutting
you know cutting paper towels and cutting tin foil. Well what do
you mean I made it a vessel? I could have used it
before, I'm just cutting it to size. So besides that there could
also be an issue of מחתך mechatech which is cutting something to
size, but that might mean a precise size. Here you do see
that like when you cut it and you create it in its
more functional use, its more appropriate sized use, that there is that
concern. Again is it biblical, is it rabbinic, but certainly there is
that concern, there's that issue. So you cannot cut the wick into
two. But רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you can use the fire
to cut it into two. So גמרא Gemara says מאי שנא בסכין
דלא, mai shena besakin delo, why can you not use a
knife? כמתקן מנא kematakin mana because you're fixing a vessel. Now there
is a debate in ראשונים Rishonim when the גמרא Gemara uses the
phrase כמתקן מנא kematakin mana does it mean it's a biblical violation
of מכה בפטיש makeh bepatish of making a vessel, or is it
a rabbinic violation because it's close to the idea of making a
vessel? But either way it's forbidden. So the גמרא Gemara says so
that's true, but אור נמי כמתקן מנא. or nami kematakin mana. So
according to that, why does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda let you use
the fire? You're also making it a vessel, who cares whether you
use a scissors or a knife or a fire? So תני רבי
חייא, tani Rabbi Chiya, so רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya taught a ברייתא
baraita which will help explain רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's position. חותכו
באור בפי שתי
נרות. chotcho ba'or befi shtei nerot. What you can do is it
can incidentally make it a vessel. What you do is you take
these two types of you know you got your two lamps here.
Let's see
I need either a what do you call it? Either a marker
or better manipulable.
Oh you got your two lamps and you've got your now I
need a string, you've got your wick that goes between the two
lamps like this. So where are you going to light the wick?
Is it going to be the wick that's coming out here, or
are you going to light it in the middle? And then the
then you're going to have the two lamps pointing like this. So
what you do is if by lighting it here in the middle
you're not actually you're basically lighting the lamp. You're not doing an
act of creating two wicks. It happens to be that that's conveniently
making it into two. Now that works better if that works better
if the whole problem is rabbinic. And if you look at רש"י,
Rashi, רש"י Rashi says בפי שתי נרות, befi shtei nerot, רש"י Rashi
says נותן שתי נרות שבתוך noten shtei nerot shebetoch anyway just two
three lines down, third line in רש"י, Rashi, דלא מוכחא דלתיקוני מנא
מחתך. delo mochiacha deletikunei mana mechatech. It doesn't make it obvious that
you're trying to make it a vessel. At blush it looks like
you're just lighting the lamp. So it's all very nice what it
looks like, but if in if you really are trying to make
two wicks, who care, who are you fooling? God? But again if
the problem is if the problem is rabbinic that it's similar to
making a vessel, and in this case it experientially it's not that
that's the focus, the sort of immediate experience is lighting of the
wicks, therefore that makes it reframes it and makes it permissible. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רב נתן בר
אבא אמר רב: Amar Rav Natan bar Abba amar Rav: מוחטין את
הפתילה ביום טוב. mochtin et haptilah beyom tov. You can needle, like
the word מחט, machat, the wick on יום טוב. Yom Tov. מאי
מוחטין? Mai mochtin? What does it mean you can needle? We actually
have that as a verb in English too, to needle somebody. So
אמר רב חנינא בר שמיה, Amar Rav Chanina bar Shemaya, but this
more literally means using a needle. אמר רב חנינא בר שמיה: Amar
Rav Chanina bar Shemaya: לאדויי חשוכה le'aduyei chashocha to remove the blackness.
Which means you take like a sharp object and you know scrape
it against the edge of the wick, it's a pre-used wick, right?
So you want to get off some of the charcoal or whatever
and maybe straighten out the threads, that you can do. That's interesting,
right? Why don't you say that's also like making a כלי? kli?
It's somewhat analogous to sharpening knives, right? You can not go ahead
and make a new knife and a knife that's not usable, but
you can sharpen a dull knife. Remember we had that before, especially
according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So here too, you can like
fix it up a little bit, you're not making it new. That
you're allowed to do. Okay.
תני בר קפרא, Tani bar Kappara,
בר קפרא Bar Kappara taught. ששה דברים נאמרו בפתילה, Sheisha devarim ne'emru
b'ptila, six things were said about a wick. ג' להחמיר וג' להקל,
Gimel l'hachmir vegimel l'hakel, three stringent rulings and three lenient rulings. להחמיר,
L'hachmir, here are the stringent rulings. אין גוזדין אותו לכתחילה ביום טוב,
Ein gozdin oto l'chat-chila b'yom tov, you can't like actually like braid
a wick on יום טוב, Yom Tov, that's really like making something,
taking strands and twisting it into a wick. ואין מהבהבין אותו
באור, Ve'ein mehavvin oto ba'ur, you cannot you cannot like char it
in the light.
That's the לשון lashon of the במה מדליקין, Bameh Madlikin, right?
Because that's what makes something, you know, easy to light is that
it's been pre-charred at the top. That would also be like making
it a vessel. ואין
חותכין אותו לשנים, Ve'ein chotchin oto lishnayim, and you can't cut it
into two. All these things are like making it a vessel.
להקל, L'hakel, three things that are lenient. ממחה ביד, Memacha b'yad,
you can like sort of smoosh it, that's a technical term anyway,
in your hand, which basically also somehow makes it more like makes
it flat and, you know, makes it more able to absorb the
oil. But that's not as that's a much more informal type of
a thing, and if you look at רש"י, Rashi, he actually says
תיקון קל על יד הוא. tikkun kal al yad hu. You know,
you're not doing it, not only would I say קל על יד
kal al yad and suggest like a שינוי shinui maybe that's part
of it, it's also not like דרך, derech, there's no like craftsman
aspect to it, there's no precision to that process. Maybe it's also
that it wasn't so unfunctional without that. Okay, again, it's interesting to
know what exactly are the lines of distinction and if you think
that the whole problem here is דרבנן, derabbanan, that it's not really
making the vessel, I don't know, maybe twisting the strings is making
of it from scratch, but these other things are not really and
it's of a more of a rabbinic issue, you can understand that
some of these at an experiential level are different and would not
be considered problematic.
You don't need expertise...
Right. ושורה בשמן, Veshora bashemen, you can immerse it in oil like
you have a pre-oiled wick, right? So, you know, you want your
wick to be pre-absorbed oil. But again, that's not like making it,
that's maybe the beginning of using it, I would also say anyway.
But they do sometimes sell, don't they sometimes sell wicks that are
like pre-oiled or whatever? And I know that some
people sell pans that are like pre-seasoned, right, that have been pre-absorbed
oil. Okay, וחותכה באור, Vechotcha ba'ur, and
here פוסק poskening like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, you can use a
fire to divide the wick if you're doing it by running it
between two lamps. ואמר רב נחמן בר אבא אמר רב, Ve'amar Rav
Nachman bar Abba amar Rav, רב נחמן בר אבא Rav Nachman bar
Abba said in the name of רב, Rav, עתירי בבל, Atirei Bavel,
the rich of בבל, Bavel, the rich people of בבל, Bavel, יורדי
גיהנם הן, yordei Gehennam hen, are going down into גיהנם. Gehennam. Why?
כי
הא, Ki ha, now, דשבתאי בר מרינוס, deShabsai bar Marinos, שבתאי Shabsai
the son of מרינוס, Marinos, איקלע לבבל, ikla l'Bavel, he's not the
rich guy, we'll see what happens. Apparently, it means that there were
a lot of wealthy people in בבל Bavel and we'll see that
they did not act properly. It's not just talking about a few
individuals, maybe about a culture. Okay, so he dropped into בבל, Bavel,
בעא מינייהו עיסקא, ba'ei mineihu iska, and he wanted to see if
he could make do some business with some of the people there.
You know, wanted to invest with them, wanted to maybe do some
little buying and selling with them. ולא יהבו ליה, velo yahavu lei,
they were not interested. Here he was, a poor guy, you know,
and they didn't want to give him a helping hand. They didn't
want to help make him like, you know, give him a job,
they were not, they completely were not interested. He wasn't asking for
a handout, doesn't matter, they didn't have see any need to help
him. מזוני, Mezonei, so then he finally he was he was sort
of reduced to asking for like a handout. He wanted just for
some food, he was starving. מיזן נמי לא זיינוהו, Meizan nami lo
zainu, they wouldn't even give him food. אמר, Amar, so he said,
הני מערב רב קאתו, hanei me'eirev rav ka'asu, oh, these people they're
not real Jews, they must have come from the ערב רב, Eirev
Rav, from the, you know, from the masses, from those, what do
they call, what's the, the riff-raff, right, the mixed multitude that were
not... they're not real Jews. Why? דכתיב, Dechsiv, because the verse says,
ונתן לך רחמים ורחמך, venasan lecha rachamim verichamcha, you know, so this
is the פסוק pasuk says about... it says actually after you'll destroy
the עיר הנדחת. Ir Haniddachas. It says, God will give you compassion
and He'll have compassion on you. And the end of the פסוק
pasuk is, כאשר נשבע לאבתיך. ka'asher nishba la'avosecha. You know, and He'll
do good to you like He swore to your fathers. So it
means, are you real descendants of your fathers? That will be to
be determined if ונתן לך רחמים, venasan lecha rachamim, if it's demonstrated
that God has given you compassion, which means that you're able to
demonstrate compassion to others. By the way, that's an important read of
the פסוק, pasuk, because normally you read the פסוק pasuk "God will
give you compassion" means "He'll have compassion on you" (ורחמך). verichamcha But
the גמרא Gemara is reading it, and a number of the מפרשי
מקרא mifarshim mikra read it, is no, the point is... because by
the way, this פסוק pasuk appears after you've wiped out the עיר
הנדחת, Ir Haniddachas, and they read it what it says, ונתן לך
רחמים. venasan lecha rachamim. You've done this tremendous, you know, cruel act
that you're commanded to do, but it was a cruel act. God
will now give you back the capacity of compassion.
capacity of compassion. So that's how the גמרא Gemara is reading it.
And that's כאשר נשבע לאבותיך. ka'asher nishba la'avotecha. So how do we
know that you are a descendant of your forefathers? By demonstrating that
you have compassion. כל המרחם על הבריות, Kol hamerachem al habriyot, anybody
that has compassion on the creatures, בידוע שהוא מזרעו של אברהם אבינו,
beyadua shehu mizar'o shel Avraham Avinu, you know that he is of
the descendants of Abraham. וכל שאינו מרחם על הבריות, vechol she'eino merachem
al habriyot, if you're not able to have compassion, בידוע שאינו מזרעו
של אברהם אבינו, beyadua she'eino mizar'o shel Avraham Avinu, you know he
is not of those descendants. And therefore, that's why we say the
rich people of בבל Bavel are going to גהינום Gehenom because apparently
they were, you know, they were Jews, but they were, there was
a real culture of not giving and not caring about those that
were in greater need. The only reason, by the way, we're mentioning
this is that it was the same אמורא Amora that spoke about
the using of the needle for the wick. It's רבי נתן בר
אבא, Rabbi Natan bar Abba, if you were wondering what this is
doing here. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues. ואמר רב נתן בר
אבא אמר רב, ve'amar Rav Natan bar Abba amar Rav, so the
same רב נתן בר אבא Rav Natan bar Abba says in the
name of רב: Rav: כל המצפה על שולחן אחרים עולם חשוך בעדו.
Kol hametzapeh al shulchan acherim olam chashoch ba'ado. If you're always looking
at what somebody else has, you're looking at the other person's table,
the whole world will look dark to you. Right? Not, you'll never
be happy with anything. You'll, you know, everything will look bleak because
you're never having enough as somebody, you know, as much as this
other person has. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as the verse says: נודד הוא ללחם
איה, Noded hu lalechem aye, he is a wanderer for bread, where
will he find bread? ידע כי נכון בידו יום חושך, yada ki
nachon beyado yom choshech, you should know that ready in your hand
is a day of darkness. So if you're always looking for bread,
meaning presumably even if you have bread, you're looking for bread, you're
never happy, you're always looking who has something better, then the whole
world will look dark and bleak. רב חסדא אמר אף חייו אינם
חיים. Rav Chisda amar af chayav einam chayim. His life isn't even
like a real life. Again, it's not exactly clear what he added
to the previous statement. It's a different like metaphor than saying, you
know, your whole life is dark or your bleak. Anyway, you don't
enjoy life, you have no sense of really living. You're always wondering
about what you could have and what you don't have. Okay, תנו
רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, now that we said that, that allows for a
transition to one final אגדתא Aggadeta statement.
ג' חייו אינם חיים, Gimel chayav einam chayim, three people, their lives
aren't really, aren't real lives. They're not, they're not really living. ואלו
הן, ve'elu hen, these are they: המצפה לשולחן חברו, hametzapeh leshulchan chavero,
what we just said, they're always like looking towards and, you know,
longing for what your, you know, your friend's table, what somebody else
has and that you don't have. So you're never actually enjoying what
you do have and, you know, living in the moment. ומי שאישתו
מושלת עליו, umi she'ishto moshelet alav, so a person, a man, I
mean, a person, but meaning a man, whose wife has dominion over
him. So there's the גמרא Gemara again speaking from the male perspective.
ומי, where's רבקה this time? ומי שיסורין מושלין בגופו, umi sheyisurin moshlin
begufo, and somebody that his body is racked with suffering, you know,
with affliction. Clearly that person is not, you know, is very a
hard, you know, you're so taken up by the pain, you know,
that it's very difficult for that person to actually feel like they're
living their life.
ויש אומרים אף מי שאין לו אלא חלוק אחד. Ve'yesh omrim af
mi she'ein lo ela chaluk echad. This is just fascinating. You always
have to love the way the גמרא Gemara has these like anti-climactic
ends sometimes to this thing. Go from very
drastic whatever the case
of the husband and wife was drastic, but anyways, two of them
were, to this case about somebody only has one shirt. Why? Because
that shirt will get filled with the, you know, with lice, it'll
get dirty and sweaty and filled with lice in particular, and therefore
that will be, he'll wind up living a miserable existence. So the
גמרא Gemara says, תנא קמא אפשר דמייני במאני. Tanna Kamma efshar de'maynei
bemanei. The first opinion that didn't mention this says: No, you could
de-louse your shirt even if you only have one shirt, so you
might not be able to take it off for a long period
to wash it, but maybe you could de-louse it while you're wearing
it. Again, very funny anti-climactic end to that. Okay, now we get
on to the next משנה. Mishnah. אין
שוברין את החרס, Ein shovrin et hacheres, we're continuing with this idea
of making vessels on יום טוב, Yom Tov, even in the context
of food and food-related activities. You cannot break a piece of pottery.
So you're going to break a pottery to use it as like
a scooper or a backscratcher, or you'll use it to cook a
fish on it, like you'll put it on top of the fire
and it'll help distribute the fire, and so you can't do that.
You're really like turning it into a vessel. ואין חותכין הנייר, ve'ein
chotchin haniyar, and you can't break a paper, לצלות בו מליח, litzlot
bo maliach, in order to roast a fish on it. So this
would be like, you know, cutting a piece of parchment paper on
יום טוב Yom Tov to use it, or a piece of tin
foil, aluminum foil.
It was papyrus, yeah?
It would be papyrus, yeah, it would not be like, right, wood-based
paper. Right. ואין גורסין, ve'ein gorsin, then it's you can't even, you
can't make vessels even in the context of אוכל נפש, ochel nefesh,
ואין גורפין את התנור והכירים, ve'ein gorfin et hatannur vehakiyrayim, and you
cannot sweep out an oven. Now why not again sweep out an
oven? Big deal, you're just removing ashes. So רש"י, Rashi, we had
this once before and רש"י Rashi again speaks about it that some
part of like the plaster or something sort of fell down and
it's really in a somewhat ruined state, and you're going to, what
you'll be doing is you'll be actually fixing it in some way.
אבל מכבשין, aval mechabshin, but what you can do is that you
can... You can pat down the ashes to make it usable in
that way.
Okay, where were we?
Right, רש״י Rashi also says that if the ashes or whatever are
too much, they'll get stuck to the food that you're cooking and
it'll ruin the food. So you can pat them against the floor
and against the walls and make it usable that way, but you
cannot really like scrape it or plaster it and fix it in
a significant way.
Okay, ואין מקיבין שתי חביות לשפות עליהן קדירה, Ve'ein makkivin shtei chaviyos
lispot aleihen kdeira, what you also cannot do is take two big
barrels and you're gonna make an ad hoc oven. What you'll do
is
you'll
take these two big barrels and you'll put them next to each
other, these two big wine barrels, and you're gonna make a fire
between them and you'll put your pot suspended by the top of
the barrels. Okay, because that's making it like an ad hoc oven,
that you cannot do. Now that's very funny because all you did
is you moved two barrels next to each other. You didn't physically
change them. So we'll see what that's about in the גמרא. Gemara.
ואין סומכין את הקדירה בבקעת, Ve'ein somchin es hakdeira bevika'at, you cannot
support a pot with a piece of wood? Yeah, exactly, with like
a beam, okay,
or like a bolt of wood. וכן בדלת, Vechein badeles, and also
by a door, which is not clear what it means, but it
sounds like it means that you can't use a detached door to
support a pot, okay, on the fire. So we'll have to see
what that's about. ואין מנהיגין את הבהמה במקל, Ve'ein manhigin es habeheima
bemakel, so now we're moving from making vessels to other things. You
cannot lead an animal with a stick on יום טוב, Yom Tov,
okay? Now is that a problem about מוקצה? muktza? Is it the
stick? Is it about עובדין דחול? uvdin dechol? Okay, what exactly is
the problem? ואין... Ve'ein... רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון מתיר, Rabbi Eliezer bar
Shimon matir, רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Eliezer bar Shimon allows. So
the last couple things related specifically to wood issues, and רש״י Rashi
says this משנה Mishnah seems to be working with the assumption that
wood by definition can only be used for fire. It's not considered
a כלי kli even if you wanted to use it for something
else and can only be used for fire. Okay, but we will
talk and that's why you can't use it to support a pot
and to lead an animal, but we'll talk about that in the
גמרא. Gemara. Let's start now with the גמרא. Gemara. מאי טעמא Mai
ta'ama says the גמרא. Gemara. What's the reason that you cannot break
the pottery or the papyrus to use in cooking? משום דקמתקן מנא
Mishum dekamsakein mana again, because you are making a vessel and even
in the context of אוכל נפש ochel nefesh that is still forbidden.
ואין גורפין תנור וכירה, Ve'ein gorfin tanur vekirayim, you cannot sweep out
the oven again in some way that you're fixing it. תני רבי
חייא בר יוסף קמיה דרב נחמן, Tani Rabbi Chiya bar Yosef kamin
d'Rav Nachman, ואם אי אפשר לאפות אלא אם כן גורפו, ve'im iy
efshar le'ofos ela im kein gorfo, but if you can't bake unless
you actually sweep it out, because otherwise the ashes will stick to
the bread or whatever, מותר, mutar, then it is permissible. Again, not
exactly clear why the sweeping out was exactly a problem altogether, but
also the fact that we give this type of an allowance also
reflects to some degree that even though the גמרא Gemara says משום
דקמתקן מנא, mishum dekamsakein mana, it might not be talking about a
biblical issue of תיקון כלי. tikun kli. These things do seem like
smaller, don't seem like necessarily what a real making of a vessel
would be. Again, some ראשונים Rishonim say it is biblical, but some
say it is only rabbinic.
Explains the halakhic ambiguity of this entire category. It's אסור assur to
do the גריפה, grifa, but if you have to...
Right. Well again, they only say that by the גריפה. grifa. They
don't say that by other things. And we should admit that the
sweeping out of the oven of all these things is the thing
that seems the least like you're making something. You're just sweeping the
ashes out. So רש״י Rashi tries to explain why it's a problem
by making it a little bit worse by saying like some plaster
fell down, it's a little broken. But the fact that the גמרא
Gemara this is the one thing the גמרא Gemara says if you
don't have a choice it's allowed seems to indicate that whatever it
was, it wasn't so bad. But I wouldn't necessarily assume that you
could apply that to the other categories, yes.
Something is missing from this discussion and something we had earlier in
the מסכת, Masechet, which is the issue that you could have done
most of these things before יום טוב. Yom Tov.
So אפשר לעשות מבעוד יום efshar la'asos mibod yom is not a
concern really by things that are directly אוכל נפש. ochel nefesh. It
is a concern about מכשירי אוכל נפש. machshirei ochel nefesh. And you
are right that these are מכשירי אוכל נפש machshirei ochel nefesh even
according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. But not necessarily a lot of...
well, some of them may be, but some of them like the
oven or whatnot might have become problematic on יום טוב Yom Tov
itself. But you do raise a good point that maybe according to
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, some of these things have the additional problem
of מכשירי... machshirei... even if מכשירי אוכל נפש machshirei ochel nefesh is
okay, the additional problem of אפשר לעשות מבעוד יום. efshar la'asos mibod
yom. Okay, that is possible, but the גמרא Gemara does not seem...
you're right, the גמרא Gemara seems to feel it's problematic even regardless
of that. Let's read a little bit more. דביתהו דרבי חייא נפלה
אריחא בתנורא. D'vassei d'Rabbi Chiya nafla aricha betanura. So this is where
רש״י Rashi is getting this idea. רבי חייא's Rabbi Chiya wife, a
brick fell down into the oven, maybe a brick from the oven
fell into it. And that sort of ruined it. It wasn't just
natural ashes and dirty. Okay, that sort would be like the scenario
רש״י Rashi is talking about not sweeping out the oven on יום
טוב. Yom Tov. There you go, Charlie, addressing your issue, it didn't
happen before, it happened on יום טוב. Yom Tov. אמר לה רבי
חייא, Amar lah Rabbi Chiya, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya said to her,
and this is like we had this line before, חזי דאנא ריפתא
מעלייתא בעינא. chazi d'ana rifta me'alyesta ba'ina. He saw that she is
about to be... So basically he
said that he said this is אי אפשר, ee efshar, there's no
way to do it without sweeping it
out. Now so therefore this idea of אי אפשר ee efshar is
again, it gives you an allowance, but only in the גמרא Gemara
in this case of sweeping out the oven.
Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ליה רבא לשמעיה,
Amar leh Rava l-shmaiyeh, רבא Rava said to his attendant, טווי לי
בר אווזא, Tavi li bar avza, roast for me a goose, I
think a בר אווזא bar avza is a goose or a duck,
I keep on getting them confused, a goose, roast for me a
goose, ואזדהר מחרוכא, ve-izdaharei me-charucha, be careful that it doesn't touch the
charcoal which will ruin it. Again, that's why you want to sweep
things out or pat them down. It touches the charcoal, it blackens
it, it ruins it. Okay. So not exactly clear, does that tell
us a הלכה? halacha? Is he telling us that therefore he's allowed
to sweep it out? Or is he what? But clearly it's talking
to us about what the issues are. Okay. So let's take a
look. One minute, just a רש״י. Rashi. Right.
Okay. One more line. אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי, Amar leh Ravina
l-Rav Ashi, רבינא Ravina said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, אמר לן
רב אחא מהוצל, Amar lan Rav Acha me-Hutzal, רב אחא Rav Acha
from הוצל Hutzal said to us, דמר שריק ליה תנורא ביומא טבא,
de-mar sharik leh tanura be-yoma tava, that the master, meaning you, he
said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, we heard
that you seal up your oven on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Meaning
what they would do is they'd put something in an oven and
then they would completely seal the door with like a plaster in
order to create this whatever the appropriate type of a hot heat
context. So how can you smear this type of a plaster around
the door of the oven? Isn't that basically like kneading? When you
make the plaster, like kneading and so on. How is that allowed?
Is that really true that you do that? So he says to
him, so he
said, אמר ליה, Amar leh, he said back to him, no, אנן
ארקתא דפרת סמכינן. Anan arkata de-Frat samchinan. I rely on the banks
of the Euphrates. This means is I get my mud from the
Euphrates. I don't make plaster. I just get pre-made mud from the
Euphrates, so it's not a
problem. והני מילי הוא דציירי מאתמול. Ve-hani mili hu de-tzayeiri me-etmol. But
it's only if you designated the mud before יום טוב. Yom Tov.
You made like a little indentation, I'm going to take from this
mud, and you made a little like marker on it, and then
it's not מוקצה muktzeh and then it's not a problem of plastering
or whatever because it's already pre-made mud. And אמר רבינא ובקטמא שרי,
Amar Ravina u-be-kitma shari, use ashes would be okay. רש״י Rashi says
ashes with water. תוספות Tosafot says no, that's also לישה, lisha, and
תוספות Tosafot says it's just to take ashes and stuff the ashes
in the crevices to seal up the oven door, that also would
be a way of doing it.